A very long time ago, maybe 6,000 years,
a fishing people came
and settled on the waters of this lake.
They're called the Mohana.
The bird fishermen.
The pelican, of all birds,
is the hardest to catch.
Ramzan, the red, calls him kodu.
Little Man.
From now on,
he's a new son for his clan.
Ramzan, the red, says his family
was the first to settle on this lake.
But another family has always
claimed that it was here long before.
The family of Mohammed, the yellow.
The pelican is the most desired of birds.
It brings honor and prosperity
to the family that owns it.
Only two families in this village
know how to capture the pelican.
Mohammed and Ramzan's.
So far this year, Mohammed,
the yellow, hasn't had the privilege.
The Mohana have a passion for birds.
Their grace and their beauty.
They need their presence
always and everywhere.
That is why they collect them.
Each family has its own bird garden.
A place outside the village.
Where they can admire them
and talk with them at leisure.
The beauty of a garden lies in the art
of finding a place for each bird,
as in a painting.
Ramzan, the red, has asked his sons
to enthrone Little Man like a king.
In a few days, the pelicans will be gone.
They come from Kazakhstan
and migrate to Arabia.
On their way, they land
for a mere three weeks on the lake.
If they land at all.
Mohammed, the yellow,
has sworn he'll get one.
And it's got nothing to do
with Ramzan, the red.
The waters of the lake
belong to Lord Zamindar.
He owns every drop.
From the deepest waters
to the unhealthiest swamps.
He is the one who grants the fishing
and hunting rights to the family.
In exchange
for granting the fishing rights,
the lord receives as tribute
half of the fish caught
and half the birds.
Every year, he redistributes
the most fish abundant waters
to the best fishermen.
The weakest always get the poorest waters.
It has been days since Mohammed,
the yellow, has fished or hunted.
He has spent all his time
hunting for a pelican.
If he is unable to make a tribute,
the lord will either reduce
his fishing territory
or take it away altogether.
Disgrace.
It's always the same thing
between Ramzan and Mohammed.
It starts with taunts.
How it ends is anybody's guess.
The whole village is involved,
including the children.
But no one dares say anything.
The pelican is a most intelligent bird.
But also one of the most dangerous.
With one stab of his beak,
Little Man can put out an eye.
It takes several days to cajole the beast.
And power.
A lot of power.
When he accepts his new family,
the bird becomes faithful
and stops acting aggressively.
It is then that Ramzan
can bring him to the village
and show him off to everyone,
as well as his own pride.
Mohammed, the yellow,
won't make a step outside his home.
He is sure that the villagers
are all making fun of him, with Ramzan.
His sons have no other choice.
As long as they don't have a pelican,
Mohammed, the yellow,
forbids them to talk to other families.
A question of dignity.
And for a Mohana son,
his father's word is law.
It's a crisis in the village.
The other families are cautious as cats.
Their every move
is judged by the two rivals.
Judged and remembered, for later.
When they were young,
Ramzan and Mohammed
were the best of friends.
But their parents fell out.
No one remembers why.
The children moved apart
and in time became enemies.
This year, Mohammed
won't have his pelican.
He must give up trying.
And think about
fishing to feed his family.
The Mohanas say they learned
everything they know from the birds.
The art of fishing and hunting,
and a lot of other things about life.
If they keep on capturing birds,
it is to observe them, to imitate them.
Captured birds attract the wild ones,
and the cycle continues.
Little Man's presence
reassures the wild ducks.
Hunting is easier with him around.
Ramzan has invited
the dignitaries from the other villages
to solemnly celebrate the pelican.
Mohammed, the yellow,
has turned down his invitation,
and Ramzan did nothing
to make him change his mind.
For Ramzan's son, it's going too far.
Vanity blinds his father.
But when you are the son of a Mohana,
you learn from birth to bend like a reed.
Old Ramzan, the red, was right.
His pelican was bound to attract another.
Just a matter of time and patience.
This new pelican
will not be for Ramzan, the red.
The conflict has gone on long enough.
Between the two families,
feuds have always created more feuds.
As usual, it is the children who try
to open the road to reconciliation.
The pride of the elders is so great
that the young ones
have to learn the art of ruse.
Migrating birds often
get tangled up in the fishermen's nets.
And this is the fishing territory
of Mohammed, the yellow.
Every year, the Zamindar organizes a race
for the most important families
of the lake.
For the first time,
Mohammed, the yellow's family
has been excluded.
With his new captive,
no one can question his skill.
And Mohammed, the yellow,
regains his full rights.
Ramzan, the red,
can have no say in the matter.
To regain full honor,
Mohammed, the yellow,
has challenged Ramzan
in the duel
that is most highly prized by the Mohanas.
The fate of a Mohana
spreads between heaven and water.
He's born on a boat
and leaves the world on the same boat.
Confiding a dream to each bird's flight.
Ramzan and Mohammed's sons
dream that this newfound peace
has returned for a good, long stay.
But what can their fathers be dreaming of?